<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The svvords abuse asserted: or, A word to the Army; shewing, the weakness of carnal weapons in spiritual warfare. The sword an useless tool in temple work: and the bearer thereof an unfit builder. Tendred to the serious consideration of His Excellency, the Lord Fairfax, and his General Councel, upon occasion of their late debates about the clause concerning religion in the promised agreement. / By John Vernon, sometimes a member of the Army.</title>
            <author>Vernon, John, fl. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95859</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V252</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E477_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204233</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863888</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863888</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162520</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95859)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162520)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 76:E477[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The svvords abuse asserted: or, A word to the Army; shewing, the weakness of carnal weapons in spiritual warfare. The sword an useless tool in temple work: and the bearer thereof an unfit builder. Tendred to the serious consideration of His Excellency, the Lord Fairfax, and his General Councel, upon occasion of their late debates about the clause concerning religion in the promised agreement. / By John Vernon, sometimes a member of the Army.</title>
                  <author>Vernon, John, fl. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>17 [i.e. 16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted for John Harris,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Decemb. 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>P. 16 misnumbered 17.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec: 19".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162520:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SVVORDS ABUSE ASSERTED: or, A word to the <hi>ARMY;</hi> SHEWING, The weakneſs of Carnal weapons in <hi>SPIRITVAL WARFARE.</hi> The Sword an Uſeleſs Tool in <hi>TEMPLE WORK:</hi> and The Bearer thereof an Unfit Builder.</p>
            <p>TENDRED To the ſerious Conſideration of His Excellency, The Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and His General Councel, upon occaſion of their late Debates about the Clauſe concerning RELIGION in the promiſed AGREEMENT.</p>
            <p>By JOHN VERNON, ſometimes a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>ARMY.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>LUKE 11.48.</bibl>
               <p>Truly ye bear witneſs, that ye allow the deed; of your fathers, for they indeed killed the Prophets, and ye build their Sepulchres.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Simulata ſanctitas eſt duplex iniquitas.</l>
               <l>Fides ſua ſponte non coacte agere vult, Chriſtus non voluit</l>
               <l>vi &amp; Gladio cogere homines ad fidem.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted for <hi>John Harris,</hi> Decemb. 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:162520:2"/>
            <head>To His Excellency, THOMAS Lord FAIRFAX, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving directed the Title Page of this little Treatiſe ſomewhat too general, and being deſirous in ſuch undertakings to ſpeak as well diſcerningly, as without reſpect to ends or perſons impartially; The aſſurance I had, and hope I have yet of your continued tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſimplicity, conſtrains me to expreſs you by my Pen, who ſtand truly in my heart amongst the leaſt Impoſtors mentioned in the following Diſcourſe: Yet this Epiſtle truly muſt forewarn you would not now in Power forget (God) your former Strength, by making filthy Policy your Refuge, in Courting any Parties, with conſent to their cruel and luſtful deſire of Reſtrictive reigning over others Conſcience; Which ſhould not onely ſoon requite many (your moſt Chriſtian Adherents) with inevitable Slavery or Ruine, for all their faithful Services; but alſo quickly overthrow our Common Peace, for which (with Thouſands ſlain) their lives and yours have been ſo long expoſed, or re-inſlave us at the beſt, in as bad as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Thraldom. And truly, my Lord, (though in God there was Mercy, yet) if you look back, there is more reaſon your Councel ſhould mourn over, then be in love with, glory in, or now repeat their laſt years Policy, henceforth deal plainly, and beware no falſe Reſerve (in Imperious breaſts) do re-divide them, and preſent the ſame advantage to your Enemy; ſo may you be unable to avoid, (through all their Policy) your own or Countreys ſadly forewarn'd of, much fear'd and threatned Slavery. Finally, be pleas'd (at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) to read over this poor Treatiſe, and if yet you finde your heart or hand to any Crime herein recorded, I much deſire in your behalf Chriſts (onely able) weapon may reſtrain it: And that <hi>Englands</hi> Common Right and Freedom may be the compleat Account of your Stewardſhip, Your ſelf alſo enjoy the Heavenly Freedom of e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Felicity, is the unfeigned deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Excellencies faithful Servant, in whatſoever h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n diſcern you faithfully ſerve your Countrey, <hi>J. V.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:162520:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The SWORDS abuſe aſſerted:</hi> OR, A word to the ARMY.</head>
            <p>HAving the priviledge to be preſent at your Conſultation about the pretended Agreement, I rejoyced greatly to hear your concurrence in ſome things indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the common welfare, which I ſhould be as ſad to ſee blaſted through Debates about Religious Worſhip, which is ſo exceedingly beyond your ſphaere and meaſure, that if not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged with ſutable ſimplicity, and more then your ordinary meekneſs and ſelf-denial, may prove the miſerable miſcarriage of that ſecond Price repoſed in your hands to improve for this oppreſſed Nation: For prevention whereof, I ſhall with all ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs proſtrate my weak aſſiſtance by advice, That you confer not with Powers or Policy in this matter; but as your ſelves would be indeed accounted Chriſtians, and not (as ſome ſuſpect) over-byaſſed, according to the exigency of Civil Intereſt, nor the inſpiration of the great things of this world; as you will allow Chriſt indeed to be Supream, and his proclaimed Law your line (at leaſt for the work of his own Worſhip and Temple) I pray you meaſure your proceedings herein by the patern of his Scriptures: For, I muſt tell you, though your policy may appear in the managing of the uncertain Affairs of an Earthly and Politique State, yet, if you intermeddle with matters beyond that ſphaere, <hi>viz</hi> The ordering of the viſible Worſhip and Service of God, wherein all are alike ſubject, and your ſelves as unskilful as any, whereunto no Terreſtial Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate hath a Grain more Title then the pooreſt Peaſant, nor is able to ſubdue the leaſt of his own or anothers ſins, and in which Kingdom Chriſt alone ſhould have the Dominion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. and wherein its ſin to be the ſervants of men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:162520:3"/>7.23. I ſay, However you determine of earthly Affairs now in your hands, to the overturning or altering ſuch Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Beware how you go about to gain any Party whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, by gratifying their proud Expectations of Dominion or Preeminence in theſe Heavenly affairs (never committed to your ſelves) leſt you be judged Infringers of, or Copartners with, whats committed alone to be both governed, ordered and ſtabliſhed for evermore in Juſtice and Judgement by the Scepter of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.7. wherein you may not adde nor diminiſh, neither alter or repeal the leaſt tittle of that moſt Royal Rule, under penalty of everlaſting ruine, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.19. For if you herein pleaſe men, you ſhall be judged by the impartial Judgement of Truth to be none of the ſervants of Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10. and conſequently Idolaters, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.21. Having thus preſented my Advice, I crave your ſingle conſideration of the enſuing Scriptures and Reaſons, which through Grace, may contribute towards the anſwering of your <hi>Quaere,</hi>
               <q>Whether the Civil Magiſtrate, though he ſhall not compel, yet may not reſtrain thoſe who profeſs not Chriſtianity from divulging their Principles, eſpecially by viſible Worſhip or Practice in Idolatry?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto, Firſt, I muſt needs affirm, That my capacity cannot diſcern your diſtinction betwixt the Compulſive and Reſtrictive Power, being fully perſwaded, That the former (though ſeemingly here excepted) is ſufficiently included in the latter; and he who hath power for the latter, ſhall by frequent reſtraining upon every frivolous occaſion, make me reſtleſs, until I read his pleaſure, That I Worſhip as he Worſhips, and ſo I feel his Power to the former. And indeed, though the Reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive may be different, as being the forerunner, yet it ever cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd in the Compulſive; and the moſt cruel of Tyrants have firſt appeared but in the Reſtrictive: and therefore the <hi>Phariſees intreat Chriſt to preach no more in their Countrey;</hi> and the Jews firſt charge the Apoſtles, <hi>To ſpeak no more in the Name of this Jeſus,</hi> before they execute the rigor of Compulſion; and ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:162520:3"/>Compulſion comes in as the conſequent, if men continue incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible after Reſtriction.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Hereby I make the Civil Magiſtrate Judge of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; which as none can aſſume without ſin, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. ſo none can conſent to, without being guilty of ſtrong endeavors to dethrone the Lord Jeſus, to whom this Judgement alone is committed, and whoſe Scepter onely can ſway the Conſcience, and ſubdue the proud imagination of the ſtouteſt Idolaters: So that its indeed a way inſufficient to effect the overthrow of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry or Antichriſtianity; wherein alſo you would bewray your great pride, in over-advancing the Civil Power, to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuing of the Word of God, which onely is able to reſtrain from Idolatry, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. and herein you would not onely be guilty of exceeding diffidence, in eſteeming ineffectual that way of his Word, which he hath eſteemed ſufficiently powerful for this work, <hi>Heb</hi> 4.12. but indeed could not diſcharge your ſelves from being guilty of making God a lyar, who hath given this record of his Son, That he alone was ſent, and ſufficiently ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the reſtraining of poor Sinners, by compelling them to the Worſhip of his Father, and that by no Humane Power or ſtriving, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.2. but <hi>by the Sword of his Mouth.</hi> And as he never aſſumed any ſuch Civil Power of reſtraining the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory, ſo he hath Commiſſioned no other with it; But to preach the Goſpel and long-ſufferance of God, which onely leads to Repentance: And this was <hi>Pauls</hi> Reſtrictive power he exerciſed upon <hi>Mars-hill,</hi> amidſt a crowd of <hi>Athenian</hi> Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, <hi>As I paſſed by and beheld your Devotions</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I found an Altar with this Inſcription,</hi> TO THE UNKNOVVN GOD; <hi>whom therefore ye ignorantly worſhip, him declare I unto you:</hi> This is a ſure way of reſtraining from Idolatry; <hi>And daily in the Jews Synagogues did Chriſt and his Apoſtles reaſon againſt Superſtition and falſe worſhip,</hi> which you will not now have ſo diſturbed: To which alſo I muſt needs give this Caution, That if Chriſt ſend a ſervant, as (its probable) ſaying, <hi>What I have revealed to you in ſecret, preach you on the houſe top; Go to the publique Synagogue in this ſeaſon of their aſſembling, which otherwiſe you cannot procure; Go, I ſay, and reaſon with them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162520:4"/>for they are in all things too ſuperſtitious,</hi> Do not you run the hazard of reſtraining in this caſe, under pretence of diſturbance: If their publique way be according to the way of Chriſt, the priviledge of Diſputing what was delivered is according to the Directory of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.22. But if their Worſhip be (as its to be feared) unſutable to the Way and Worſhip of Chriſt, take heed of reſtraining thoſe that would go ſingly to ſhew them a better way, leſt you conclude Chriſt (whoſe Practice was, and Precept is, the ſame) a diſturber. But</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The conviction of the Underſtanding being the foundation of Converſion, and that being a faculty which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be forced, nor ſatisfied without an overcoming Reaſon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing over what it hath firſt received. A powerful Argument would ſoon ſubdue that noble part, when Civil Reſtraint would increaſe prejudice, and confirm obſcurity; and therefore the way of God is rather, <hi>Come, let us reaſon together;</hi> and, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you therefore, Brethren, by the tender mercies of God</hi> (or, foraſmuch as God is thus merciful) <hi>that you offer up your bodies a living ſacrifice, holy and acceptable, which is your reaſonable ſervice, &amp;c.</hi> This is a Chriſtians way of reſtraining; Which Apoſtle alſo commends the <hi>Bereans</hi> nobility, for refuſing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him implicitely, until they were confirmed in the truth of his Doctrine by ſcrutiny: And, I ſay, a noble Spirit the Carnal Sword can never reſtrain, but who ere attempts it, ſhall but partake (at beſt) in other mens Hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Humane Reſtriction is ſo inconſiſtent with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry name and nature of the Goſpel, that a man cannot mention ſuch a thing, without including himſelf amongſt the Enemies thereof: If your preſident for it be from the Law (wherein indeed ſuch Reſtriction would better ſuit with literal ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, eſpecially the Reſtrainers being as well Typical as the Sacrifices) <hi>You are debtors to the whole Law, to do it;</hi> and, <hi>Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing:</hi> But if you indeed purſue Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity as you pretend, why propoſe you ſuch Oppoſition to it? which imports nothing but a proffer of Peace, Love, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, glad Tidings, Freedom, and not forcible reſtraint, even
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:162520:4"/>to the pooreſt of Captives, to flat Idolaters; and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, Violence, Fury, deſire after Civil Power to reſtrain, &amp;c. is the lively Character of men not yet reformed by the power of the Goſpel: This was poor <hi>Pauls Damaſcus</hi> work, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.2.13. which he ſo much diſowned, <hi>Verſe</hi> 22. when he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed taſted the more milde nature of Chriſtianity. Moreover, if your Policy be not become Scripture proof, I ſhall propoſe ſome ſo plainly poſitive againſt this Reſtrictive Power, that I believe you cannot reaſonably evade; as, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.28. If you pleaſe to peruſe that place, you ſhall perceive a zealous ſervant for the honor of Chriſt, diſcerning clearly the Enemies of Chriſt, and was alſo told they were ſuch by Chriſt, apparent Idolaters, for they were the viſible children of the Devil, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to Tares; of a very ill quality, eſpecially growing Tares, the moſt at enmity with Wheat of any Weed that groweth: Well, the Servant deſires to deſtroy them, <hi>No,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>leſt you pluck up the wheat likewiſe:</hi> Yes, but might he not reſtrain them? <hi>No, let them grow,</hi> &amp;c. from which Anſwer I conceive may be clearly and ſafely concluded, That men, though the ſervants of Chriſt, and clearly diſcerning his Enemies, may not yet pluck them up, or reſtrain them by a Humane Power with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out treſpaſs, againſt the expreſs command of Chriſt, who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that work to his Harveſt, the end of the world, &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 38. Fifthly, Its the moſt uſual thing in the world for Chriſtians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to be plucked up and reſtrained, though under other Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and that perhaps might be the Reaſon why Chriſt refuſed to ſuffer any reſtraining preſident, though by a Tare-diſcerning ſervant: I pray you then agree you to none in our Erroneous age, wherein is nothing more common then to put a Chriſtian into a Bears skin, when men intend to bait him, and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate (ſo called) as prone to miſcal good evil, and evil good as any.</p>
            <q>I but ſay ſome, though the Magiſtrate Queſtion any, if he do but ſay Sir, I profeſs Chriſtianity, its ſufficient to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>To which I Anſwer, That let him ſay what he will, it muſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:162520:5"/>not then be as the accuſed ſays, but as he whom you make Judge determines in theſe Reſtrictive caſes, which if any people could poſſibly, or durſt be ſo brutiſh to betruſt, With whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhould preſume the execution hereof, I am perſwaded it would be more effectual to ſay
<note n="*" place="margin">Mar. 7.11.</note> 
               <hi>Corban,</hi> then, Sir, I am a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, to free me from his ſnare: And ſure I am, let a man ſay what he will for himſelf, he cannot ſay more then Chriſt Jeſus could (and did) for the clearing of his innocency; and yet the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictive Sentence <hi>(Nemine contradicenti)</hi> concluded him a Blaſphemer, a Wine-bibber, a Companion with Harlots, a man not fit to live, becauſe he would not be reſtrained, &amp;c. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed do the moſt cruel amongſt Tyrants perſecute or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain Chriſtians, as Chriſtians, but under other horrid criminal Notions, &amp;c. which have ever been a poor Chriſtians portion, as being the ſtanding Principle of all oppreſſing Powers, to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie, that they may pluck up or reſtrain whomſoever they cannot otherways more voluntarily ſubject unto their luſts; Witneſs the Ordinance of Parliament lately renewed, for the reſtraining and puniſhing of men as Blaſphemers and Sectaries, even with Death, for many Points conſonant with ſound Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo unskilful are our Civil Stewards in ſuch Affairs; nor can any commit ſuch truſt unto them, becauſe they could not indeed give, nor the people who ſhould betruſt them could poſſibly take, an account from them in ſuch caſes, ſo confuſed is the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the univerſal, that we cannot expect a concurrance of any party conſiderable in the Nation, in Principles of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and, I hope, there's none that aſpire to any power, but what the People ſhall inveſt them with, and may repeal, as they ſhall ſee ſuch their Servants proceedings conduce to or againſt their common ſafety, which by Nature all men are enabled to determine. Or if any amongſt you ſhall contend for other Power, then whats thus betruſted in his hands, and himſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable unto thoſe who betruſted him, he ſhal not free himſelf from being a Tyrant, ſeeking ſome private Factions, or his own ſingle Intereſt, to the ſubverting of the Common Freedom, and ſo ought to be proceeded againſt according to your own patern or preſident, againſt him or them who thus before op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d us.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:162520:5"/>
            <p>Moreover the fury of <hi>Smectimnius</hi> and others, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times groaning under this reſtraint themſelves, having yet in their deliverance and arbitrarily uſurped power uſed the ſame violence not only to their fellow ſufferers, but towards even thoſe who waſted themſelves to effect their freedom, (though we might in faith, which yet no friend to Chriſt dares aſſert,) yet conſidering the common frailty, eſpecially in men, deputed to publique Truſt, the beſt of whom have not well diſcharged their ſix years Seſſion, as civil Repreſentatives, through their continuing ſo long unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable ſhall I truſt ſufficiently forewarn us, that we depute no ſuch power, whereof they cannot poſſibly be accountable, except we will herein become the ſinful ſervants of men, and ſet them up in the ſtead of Chriſt, yea to Lord it over the flock of Chriſt, and ſit Judg as if in the room of Chriſt, which as none can do without moſt Antichriſtian Tyranny, ſo none can deſire to depute him to without partaking of his great Iniquity; for indeed this is the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, to deny Chriſt come in the Fleſh, by depriving him of his Offices; and though your ſelves ſhould ſay, you profeſs Chriſt, and yet contend (as herein) to aſſume the kingly Office of Chriſt, you will be found no ſuch friends, as you eſteem your ſelves, to Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, if we ſhould reflect unto former times, ſhould we conſider poor <hi>Iſraels</hi> poſſeſſing the <hi>Canaanities</hi> ſins with their Nation? <hi>Amazaahs</hi> adoring the gods of <hi>Seir,</hi> when he had redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the <hi>Edomites,</hi> 2 Chron. 25.14. and inumerable ſuch examples, both in priſtine and preſent time, would ſo confirm any faithful man in the frailty of the moſt faithful and deſerving; that though they ſhould fray away the horns of former oppreſſors, <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.21. he would not repoſe to him any ſuch reſtrictive power in ſpiritual caſes, (wherein he cannot poſſible be accountable,) nor indeed any civil Truſt without conſtant account, as occaſion ſerves, how he hath performed it: For in the firſt he ſhould be abſolutely guilty of dethroning the Lord Jeſus; by the latter alſo he would incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage men (as of late) to ſuch corruptions, that to keep themſelves from account, they would endeavor to enſlave thoſe who intruſted them.</p>
            <p>I muſt add one word more to the unfitneſs of the Magiſtrate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:162520:6"/>all others, as conſidering how much more Self-Denial it would require in him then in another, to be ſingle in theſe affairs, as conſidering him, continued by the conſent, and originally the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective of the people, who, though he might be fit enough for civil and accountable ſervices, which every carnal ſpirit would for ſelf ſake ſeek to preſerve, yet probably not the quainteſt choice to be Judg in matter of Chriſtianity. More might be ſaid to the ſpirit of thoſe men whom you deſire to delude with this compliance, as how much it would incourage them to what your conſcience knows they are too much inclin'd: How much you would ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and make proviſion for their ſin and future cruelty: How much indeed you would promote moſt foul Idolatry, and fill the world with Phariſees and Hypocrites, and that not from the Spirit of Chriſt, I am ſure, but plain Self-Intereſt.</p>
            <p>I ſhould too far treſpaſs now to be more tedious, and my inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency reproves my wading far in ſuch a weighty ſubject. I will preſent you with another Scripture, and haſten to a period, but I pray you conſider it impartially, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24. <hi>The ſervant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive,</hi> (for his Maſter did it not, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42:2.) <hi>but be gentle,</hi> (gentleneſs, it ſeems, beſt befits a Chriſtian, and reſtrains the rebellious,) <hi>unto all men who oppoſe themſelves,</hi> (poor Naturaliſts, Jews, Heathens, Idolaters, &amp;c.) yea (ſaith that word) to thoſe that are ſo in the ſnares of the Devil, that they are taken captive, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, at his pleaſure; and this ſimple way is the Lord Chriſts way of reſtraining: Though it confound the wiſdom of the wiſe, and be accounted an inlet to all manner of Libertiniſm, eſteemed leſs then the carnal weapon, &amp;c. yet this way Chriſt hath choſen, as his mighty way of reſtraining; hee'l have no unwilling worſhipers, no civil reſtraining; A word of glad tydings, the Goſpel of Peace, is that which he proclaims to poor Idolaters; and this is the ſword which he alone will allow of to reduce the rebellious, and make the worſt of them a willing people in this day of his Power: If that this weapon were more well managed amongſt us, your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying one would be much more diſeſteemed, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Truly friends, you know not what ſpirit you are of in this ſword<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtraining deſire, &amp;c. If <hi>England</hi> ſhould now call to an account her late civil Stewards, I ſee they are not able to give an account of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162520:6"/>their earthly ſtewardſhip: Moſt of them drunk with Iniquity, Pride, Paſſion, Oppreſſion, Tyranny, protecting the rich and their great relations untaxed, without pity, grinding the face of the poor, cannot loſe the leaſt luſt to ſet the captive and the oppreſſed at liberty, Partial, Extortioners, Lovers of pleaſure, and humane praiſe, what not, that may compleat a wicked one, &amp;c. Moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionably covetous, which the Word of God declares to be flat Idolatry, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p>And how ſhall we truſt theſe (if we could truſt any) with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining, &amp;c? No my friends, if your faces be indeed toward the welfare and freedom of the Nation, conſult rather how you may, in your place and ſphere, reſtrain the rage of our civil wrongs, and great agrievances, by laying a ſure Foundation for our Countries Freedom: Confer with your fellow-Freemen of <hi>England,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, with ſingleneſs of ſpirit, ſay unto them, truly you were the life of our power, by you we were lifted up into theſe places which men call Honorable: It's our honor truly to ſerve you in your diſtreſs, which is our own alſo: Your money and other aſſiſtance, hath been the ſinews of our Service: and our Service having been proſpered to effect our mutual Peace, pray let's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult how we may be ſetled in a more firm Quiet to univerſal Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: How we may be united againſt the firſt appearance of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, &amp;c. This language would be your Laurel indeed; you might then ſit down with great content, acknowledging Gods goodneſs in chuſing you (the moſt contemptible) to be ſo ſerviceable to your native Country. But alas, with ſorrow, even to impatiency, do I conſider, that after this Nation hath been theſe ſeven years languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under a Bloody Flux, and but beginning to recover, that any of her (eſteemed) Doctors ſhould, like unmerciful Mountebanks, diſplay their policy by trying concluſions with an almoſt conſumed Nation! Oh how dare any Chriſtian contend for the continuing (yea, by a free Agreement, ſupporting and renewing) of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining power which hath been from age to age, ſince Chriſt was crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to this preſent time, the known ſupporter of the Dragons Creſt! Oh let all that call themſelves Chriſtians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware they pleaſe not men on ſuch accounts, leſt they cruelly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract upon themſelves all the righteous blood that hath been ſhed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:162520:7"/>ſince <hi>Abel,</hi> by juſtifying Chriſtian crucifiers, in pleading for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictive power, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But you will ſay, What the Jewiſh Magiſtrates puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as evils and diſcernable by the light of nature, Magiſtrates may puniſh now? But the Magiſtrates reſtrained Idolaters of old, and that as being againſt the light of nature, and ſo they may now.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to this, let us examine the true ground of Idolaters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing puniſhed, and we ſhall find in it theſe three things remarkable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they never puniſhed them, till they were commanded from Heaven to do it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The people, as well as the Magiſtrate, had a hand in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Idolater, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The puniſhment is exactly there deſcribed, and ſo, if we make that our rule, we muſt not mangle it according to our own imaginations; But death even to wives or ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſt relations was here commanded, and yet as well for ſecret as publique Idolatry: Neither were Idolaters ſuffered to live in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but to be driven out. Beſides, they had a compulſive power, as well as a reſtrictive, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. All which indeed did lively repreſent, in every of thoſe particulars, the power of Chriſt, and the ſpiritual order of his Church in the Goſpel, and hath now no relation to any Nation or Civil Power whatſoever, which to affirm would but render the obſerver mainly diſobedient to his own rule, which requires exact obedience; ſo alſo would it thwart the very drift of the Goſpel, which is, without reſpect to any nation, tongue or kindred, to gather out of every nation a people unto Chriſt: and therefore, in order to that work, his ſervants are to converſe with Idolaters, and may have civil ſociety with them alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. I might ſpeak yet to the vaſt diſagreement betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and their Magiſtrates; but I think no man, except ſuch who plead now National Churches for their profit, or abſolute Monarchy through their aſpiring hope, can well conceit a paralel.</p>
            <p>Yet if you deſire to be Reſtrainers of falſe worſhip, ſeeing the civil Sword in ſpiritual affairs is the ſupporter of the beaſt &amp; not Chriſts way of reſtraining, it remains that we uſe Chriſts weapons only in his work, and rather that you pity poor Idolaters, even as God for Chriſts ſake pityed us; And, conſidering that ſuch were all of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:162520:7"/>you, that you now apply your ſelves ſuitably to ſuccor ſuch poor creatures, who oppoſe themſelvs; beſeeching them, as if in Chriſt ſtead, to be reconciled unto God: convincing their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and ſo reſtraining them from Idolatry. You who call your ſelves Chriſtians, giving no occaſion of ſtumbling by a vain conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, &amp;c. ſhould hereby add much to the reſtraint of falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, yea and compel to the true, if your ſelves walked Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in it: When by aſſuming to confer on others a power which never was, nor can ſafely be committed to your ſelves, you ſhould become the chief in reſtraining of Chriſtianity, in ſowing of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood, and reaping hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But would you then have Idolaters to dwell amongſt us? Men may then live as they liſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I would neither have them live as they nor as you liſt, but wiſh that you, as they, were more led by light and truth, ſetting you free from all falſe ways, attempts, and worſhips: But I would indeed have all Jews or Heathens, or what ever Ignorants are Native, with all ſuch Forreign you invite to traffique and ſuffer to inhabit, as freely to Converſe as Commerce with you, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſtraint upon religious Cauſes; and that you would conſider your ſelves might never have been converted, if you ſhould not ſo have been freely ſuffered; nor that you would, by any practice in your pride, reprove Chriſt for providing no other way to reſtrain Idolatry. I have heard of a few Chriſtians that wrought righteouſneſs over Idolatrous Nations by the power of their word, but never of Idolaters that ſo ſubverted Chriſtians; for its the word of Chriſts patience, and a name written in the book of life ſhall preſerve and eſtabliſh them, when all the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fideſhall wonder after the beaſt and worſhip him; they can freely converſe with Heathens, and account it their meat and drink, yea it ſhall renew their ſtrength to diſcourſe with poor Idolaters, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in their publique aſſemblies: You that have taſted of the Word of Chriſt, know this to be the reſtrictive power and way of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But if you will allow this, we may quickly have our civil State ſubverted?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this the experience of other Nations might be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:162520:8"/>anſwer: let any man conſider the flouriſhing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the Low Countries ever ſince they ſuffered e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man to worſhip according to his Conſcience, and even the Lews themſelves to worſhip in their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Synagogues; And let it be obſerved, that whileſt every man enjoys his Liberty, it is his proper Intereſt to endeavor the Preſervation of that Common-wealth (for in that he preſerves himſelf,) and in the ſubverſion of ſuch a State no ſort of people could be gainers, only it might be the Intereſt of one, or ſome few men, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to tyrannize over the reſt. But there would be no great danger of their prevailing, becauſe the whole multitudes Intereſt lead them to oppoſe any ſuch at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts. Yet if a fuller anſwer be thought neceſſary, I may ſhew clearly that there is no danger of the ſubvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the State, by reaſon of every mans worſhiping God according to his Conſcience; For a State cannot be ſubverted but either by force, or by a general conſent of the people. The Force is eaſily prevented, when the firſt thirty men, meeting in Arms for any ſuch end, are by the Law Traytors, and may be proceeded againſt accordingly; and I ſuppoſe no man will imagine it poſſible to ſubvert the State by a general conſent of the People, when there will be ſuch a variety of judgments, and every man is free, and in fear of a change, leſt he be a loſer by it.</p>
            <p>Finally, having through the Diſcourſe declared the civil Steward no fit reſtrainer nor determiner of what's Idolatry; I would not now be thought I judg you free from that foul ſin, to whom I ſpeak, who act ſo fierce for this reſtraint; nor call I that the moſt groſs Idolatry which you account ſo, but the more ſpiritual extract,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:162520:8"/>the more ſtrong and deſperate, except it ſhall be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictive ſin, that one cannot ſo skilfully cloak his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption as another, and that ſnare indeed would take the ſimpleſt, and looſe the ſubtileſt ſinners; but Chriſt, who ſhall be Judg, will far more righteouſly, and acquit poor dumb Idolater, as ſoon as one that calls himſelf a Chriſtian, and yet walks not accordingly: His is the way of Truth, and all ways elſe are but Imaginary. Examine your ſelves, whether you walk in the Faith, and are freed from flat Idolatry. The Diſciple <hi>John</hi> laying down ſure Principles before a People not inclined to dumb Idolatry, yet ſaw great occaſion to ſum up all with this exhortation, <hi>Little children keep your ſelves from Idols,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> v. 21. which compared with <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. Would be, I fear, fit counſel for you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; and truly when I conſider the uncertain found this day amongſt many, who oft Trumpet out the word Chriſtianity, but yet by far exceed the Native <hi>Indian</hi> in fallacious fancies, alledging the leadings forth of God by his infallible and tranſparent Spirit, to their moſt inextricable abſurdities; and what recent my ſelf have had, and ſome have ſtill of ſuch their flaſhes, it makes me tremble to conceipt how unfit frail man at beſt is for reſtrictive power in theſe affairs, &amp;c. I will ſhut up all with this aſſertion, That Chriſtians and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens in civil offences are alike ſubjected to the civil Sword, and pretence to the former would aggravate his miſdemeanor, but neither ſubject in religious cauſes, and there can be no ſuch reſtraint where there muſt be no ſuperiority. What <hi>Salmeron</hi> obſerved upon <hi>John</hi> 2.4. may as fitly be applyed to our Publique Deputies, as to Parents; <hi>In cauſa Religionis Conſanguineos non eſse
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:162520:9"/>Audiendos nee reſpiciendos.</hi> Now the God of Wiſdom reſtrain you from your ways, and compel you to his Will; but if ye now draw back from his pleaſure to your own policy, (let your end be never ſo good,) <hi>My Soul ſhall have no pleaſure in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUt one ſtrange Argument for reſtrictive Power came to my ear ſince the concluſion; and ſome I underſtand do ſtart this Quaere from the word Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; How can it be called an Agreement of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple when many thouſands there are, (who are otherwiſe faithful) yet in conſcience cannot conſent or ſubſcribe to it, if ye diſallow of this civil reſtrictive Power, &amp;c. and ſo ſhall be deprived of their other Priviledges? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That the Title (An Agreement) imports nothing without relation to the ſubſtance following, which is for the Foundation of future Peace &amp; Freedom, and he that lays a foundation of ſlavery to pleaſe oppreſſors, when he proclaims out Freedom, ſhal not anſwer that Agreement, but the carnal heart of a deceitful Tyrant. Nor deſerves he to be accounted faithful, but deprives himſelf of profer'd Priviledg and Freedom that cannot ſubſcribe or agree thereto, except he may make all others his ſlaves. Which pride, I hope, no Chriſtian will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, nor take are to gorge his Pallet with Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an (reſtrictive Power,) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ho at eaſier rates will not agree to Common Right and Freedom.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>Soli deo Gloaia.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
